Speaker 1: the national debt just hit $38 trillion. Congratulations, America. Congress spent every
Speaker 1: penny. $38 large comes to $287,000 for every household in America with another $140,000 in
Speaker 1: private debt. And it comes just two months after we crossed $37 trillion back on August 12th. As
Speaker 1: in, we're now running an annualized $5.1 trillion of additional debt, which is two and a half times
Speaker 1: the headline deficit. It also comes to $40,000 in new debt for every household in America last year.
Speaker 1: In other words, you could have bought a nice car last year with cash. Instead, Congress blew it.
Speaker 1: For perspective, $38 trillion is roughly one-third of all the M2 money in the whole world.
Speaker 1: So this amount of debt is doing three things. First, it is escalating debt interest payments,
Speaker 1: which go on top of existing debt. Yes, we borrow every penny. Second, it's raising interest rates
Speaker 1: as federal borrowing crowds out everything else, business loans, personal loans, mortgages. Third,
Speaker 1: it's raising concerns among investors, people who buy all that debt, whether government will actually
Speaker 1: pay it back. So the Congressional Budget Office now projects $140 trillion of debt by 2054,
Speaker 1: which is literally more than all the money in the world. So will they pay it back? Now,
Speaker 1: about 81% of voters say they care about federal debt in polls, but it ranks very low, typically around
Speaker 1: number 10 or 12, down with transgenders in sports. Presumably because in the back of their minds,
Speaker 1: voters know it will never be paid back. It is just numbers. But it's not just numbers to the investors
Speaker 1: who buy these bonds, including every major bank and pension fund. They're already driving up interest rates,
Speaker 1: in fear of default, as driving the so-called debasement trade, gold and silver, as investors
Speaker 1: worry that they'll let inflation run to reduce the debt, which increases the value of gold and silver.
Speaker 1: This actually happened under Biden, where he added $8 trillion in debt, but the debt-to-GDP ratio
Speaker 1: actually went down because of inflation. In the extreme case, Weimar Germany used inflation to shrink
Speaker 1: their crippling national debt to the price of a loaf of bread. Alas, Biden crashed out before we
Speaker 1: got the loaf of bread. Even worse is a hard default, where they simply stopped paying. This happens in
Speaker 1: states all the time. In 2008, California, Arizona, and Illinois paid in IOUs. New York famously did in
Speaker 1: the 70s. It also happens in countries all the time, usually basket cases like Venezuela or Sri Lanka,
Speaker 1: but also in rich countries when some clever politician realizes that voters enjoy stiffing
Speaker 1: Wall Street and China who own the debt. That's exactly what happened in Greece in 2012, where the
Speaker 1: prime minister decided to stiff the greedy German bankers who owned Greeks foreign debt. This set off
Speaker 1: a default crisis across Europe, ultimately bailed out with 30% of the GDP involved. So in US terms,
Speaker 1: that's about a $6 trillion bailout. So what's next brought to you by I Trust Capital. $140 trillion by
Speaker 1: 2054 is a comic book number, but CBO says it's coming, and it will almost certainly be defaulted,
Speaker 1: whether hard or soft with inflation. The easy fixes are cut spending or balanced budget amendment,
Speaker 1: which will not happen, meaning either we fix the money and the Fed with gold, or it is a combination
Speaker 1: of periodic default and permanent inflation that will really make that gold, silver, or Bitcoin shine.
Speaker 1: Read the rest with charts and all the gory details at ProfSynos.com. Okay, we'll be watching. See you next time.